Guide to the Board of Trustees records, 1821-2003 RG0001
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Committees, 1911-1960; RG0001 Series 5; 4 Linear feet (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5, Box 6, Box 7, Box 8)
  - Committee on Extracurricular Activities--meeting minutes, 01/23/1956 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    Text on folder "No minutes"
  - Committee on Extracurricular Activities--meeting minutes, 09/08/1948 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Committee on Extracurricular Activities--meeting minutes, 10/23/1947 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    Text on folder "Expanding Athletic Program. Hatchet"
  - Committee on Extracurricular Activities--meeting minutes, 01/10/1947 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    Text on folder "Need for playing fields--transportation must be furnished. Mr. Farrington instructed to investigate possibilities. Salary of Coach Stahley. Student fee of $10.00 per smester suggested."
  - Committee on Extracurricular Activities--meeting minutes, 02/08/1943 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    Text on folder "Additions to athletic budget for football and basketball. Discussion of possibility of playing football in fall of 1943 and decision to notify teams on schedule of the probability of non-performance of contracts. Discussion of services of Director Busick and Coach Baker in the event of discontinuance of football,"
  - Committee on Extracurricular Activities--meeting minutes, 05/27/1943 (Box 3, Folder 76)
    Text on folder "Recommendation for discontinuance of intercollegiate athletics for the duration."
  - Committee on Extracurricular Activities--meeting minutes, 12/07/1942 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    Text on folder "Cue and Curtain. Handbook. The case of William J. Reinhart. Southern Conference"
  - Committee on Extracurricular Activities--meeting minutes, 07/31/1942 (Box 3, Folder 78)
    Text on folder "Discontinuance of University Band for duration of war. Selection of editor and manager of HATCHET. Change in form of student HANDBOOK. Athletics: personnel, purchase of bus, playing of freshmen in Southern Conference"
  - Committee on Extracurricular Activities--meeting minutes, 05/29/1942 (Box 3, Folder 79)
    Text on folder "Report of the Chairman to the Board on athletic policy"
  - Committee on Extracurricular Activities--meeting minutes, 07/09/1941 (Box 3, Folder 80)
    Text on folder "Resignation of Professor Claud Max Farrington. Appointment of Mr. Reinhart as Associate Director of Physical Education. Appointment of Mr. Farrington on part-time basis. Creation of Assistant Professorship of Physical Education for Men. Creation of Assistant Directorship of Physical Education for Men"
  - Committee on Extracurricular Activities--meeting minutes, 06/23/1941 (Box 3, Folder 81)
    Text on folder "Organization of Committee. Trustee Freer named as Secretary. Functions of Committee. Outline of development of Athletics in University."
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs--meeting minutes, 11/28/1960 (Box 3, Folder 82)
    Text on folder "Reports concerning property purchased during fiscal year 1959-60; an analysis of real estate holdings of the University; a statement of indebtedness; a statement showing relation of value of land and buildings to plant indebtedness of various colleges and universities. Resolution authorizing the purchase of property to the amount of $500,000 during fiscal year ending August 31, 1961. Resolution authorizing the Finance Committee to mortgage property to the extent of $500,000, if necessary to carry out the property acquisition program of the Buildings and Lands Committee. The meeting adjourned."
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs--meeting minutes, 03/07/1960 (Box 3, Folder 83)
    Text on folder "Tuition fees to be effective Sept. 1, 1960, approved by Committee. Summary of proposed operating budget for 1960-61 approved. Comparative financial highlights for the years 1949, 1958, and 1959 reviewed by the Committee. Resolution concerning a Group Life Insurance Plan approved by Committee. The Committee adjourned."
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs--meeting minutes, 01/22/1960 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    Text on folder "Report by Mr. Van Devanter concerning the University Investment Portfolio. Approval of extension of real estate loan held by Riggs National Bank in the amount of $350,000, secured by the deed of trust on Old Hospital and Medical School properties, for five year at 51/2%. Approval of resolution to substitute the name of H.J. Cantini for that of John A. McLaughlin (former resolution adopted Oct. 13, 1955). Approval or recommendation to amend Section 9 of Chapter 5 of the By-Laws concerning "access to the saftey deposit box" to note change in Treasurer's title and to provide access to the box when a member of the Finance Committee is not available. The Finance Committtee recommended that authority granted by Board to the Buildings and Lands Committee be increased to $800,000; That the authority granted to Finance Committee on Ovtober 8, 1959 be amended so the Committee can mortgage property to the extent of $800,000 to carry out property acquisition program of the Committee on Buildings and Lands. Approval of temporary transfer of funds ($200,000) from Current Funds Surplus-Appropriated for Hospital" to "Current Funds - Unappropriated". Approval of Auditor's certificate. The committee adjourned."
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs--meeting minutes, 07/15/1959 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    Text on folder "Approval of recommendation that during 1959-60 fiscal year the Committee on Buildings and Lands be authorized to purchase properties within the expenditure of $400,000, for the fiscal year in certain squares. Approval of recommendation that during 1959-60 fiscal year the Finance Committee be authorized to mortgage University income-producing properties to the extent of $400,000 to carry out the property acquisition program recommended above by the Buildings and Lands Committee."
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs--meeting minutes, 02/16/1959 (Box 3, Folder 86)
    Text on folder "Discussion of securities received from the DeKnight Estate; decision to sell all bond issues except $2,000 par value Wash. Gas Light Co., to retain the preferred stock issue, the 12 common stock issues and 5 real estate note issues and to add the retained investments to the Consolidated Endowment Funds at their market value on date of receipt from the American Security & Trust Co. Committee suggested that Mr. Van Devanter review all the preferred stock holdings of the University in the light of present market conditions. The Committee thought its statement of April 24, 1957, establishing a limitation of $50,000 for investment of endowment funds in any individual company should be reviewed and a new basis for a desirable limit be established. Pending adoption of a new basis, it was agreed that Investment Counsel could bring to Committee recommendations for purchase of more than $50,000 in one company if the investment seemed to merit the purchase of such an amount."
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs--meeting minutes, 07/03/1958 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs--meeting minutes, 03/11/1958 (Box 3, Folder 88)
    Text on folder "It was recommended that the Auditor's Report be presented to the Board for acceptance. It was voted to defer making any recommendation to the Board in reference to appointment of auditors for next fiscal year until the May Board Mtg. Committee voted to present statement of Comparative Financial Highlights to the Board at its next meeting. Committee approved tuition fees, special fees and dormitory charges to be effective September 1, 1958. Approval of proposed budget for1958-59 and it was recommended the budget be presented to the Board for adoption. The Committee adourned [adjourned] at 3:00 o'clock."
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 02/27/1958 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Text on folder "Treasurer Herzog was requested to have a revised loan agreement prepared (covering funds borrowed for purchase and remodeling Dolly Madison Hall and John Quincy Adams Hall) in accordance with understanding reached with the Housing and Home Finance Agency. Treasurer Herzog recommended the firm of Covington and Burling as Bond Counsel. The Committee authorized employment of this firm. Auditor's certificate reviewed. Recommendation that Price Waterhouse & Co. be retained as auditors for 1958-59."
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 12/09/1957 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Text on folder "Comparative Summary of Portfolio of Endowment Funds as of August 31, 1957 was presented to the Committee."
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 04/24/1957 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Text on folder "Committee authorized investment of the Ford Foundation Grants and maturing U.S. Treasury Bills, in 90 Day Bills on a "roll over" basis until longer acceptable investments at better yields are available. Reinvestment to be in a new bond issues. Presentation of Comparative Summary of Portfolio of Endowment Funds to be presented to the Board semi-annually. Recommendation concerning limitation on investment in common stock. To ask Board to rescind action of March 11, 1937, and authorize investment in common stocks not to exceed 45% of the book value. One more member to be added to the Finance Committee. Chairman of the Committee and President to recommend person. Investment in one company to be limited to $50,000, unless Investment Counsel recommends otherwise."
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 03/02/1956 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Text on folder "The following recommendation were approved: 1. Employment of Mr. Winslow B. Van Devanter as Investment Counselor effective April 1, 1956, subject to 30 days cancellation notice - replacing Lionel D. Edie & Co., Inc. 2. Purchase of 400 shares General American Transportation Corp. stock. 3. Employment of Price Waterhouse & Co. as auditors, effective at beginning of current fiscal year - replacing R.G. Rankin & Co. 4. Authorization to utilize excess cash funds for investment in U.S. Treasury Bills or Govt. maturities of less than one year, not to exceed $300,000. 5. Authorization to purchase or sell fractional shares issued on equities held in University portfolio. 6. Authorization to sell securities given to Univ. for expendable purposes in near future - up to $2,000 market value with the approval of one member of the Committee; if greater value, approval of a majority of the Committee is required. 7. Authorization to exchange short term Governments on rollovers. To present, with advice of legal counsel, a resolution to the Board covering distribution of income of Consolidated Endowment Funds, effective 9/1/55, on the basis of shares established for each participating fund rather than book value. Consideration of changes in Chapter V, Section 9 of the By-Laws; approved change in terminology of Comptroller to Treasurer and Asst. Comptroller to Asst. Treasurer, but decided against any change in the policy of who might have access to the securities."
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 05/12/1954 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Text on folder "1954-55 Budget review. Suggestion by Trustee Tompkins for doctors office on north half of Square 40 if Medical Building were located on that square."
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 02/28/1953 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, "Results of Current Operations: Analysis of Current Operations, 1947 -1952 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, List of GWU stock and bond investments, 05/31/1945 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, List of GWU stock and bond investments, 05/05/1943 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, Report of the Chairman to the Board, 05/29/1942 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 03/04/1942 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, Report to the Board, 04/09/1941 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, Report of the Finance Committee of GWU, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, Report of the Finance Committee of GWU, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 02/08/1940 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 12/06/1939 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 12/08/1937 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Text on folder "Purchase of Lot B, - H St., Lot 4 and Lot 803 - G St."
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 05/04/1937 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Text on folder "Re: Lionel D. Edie & Co."
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 03/11/1937 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    Text on folder "re: Investment Counsel"
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 03/02/1937 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 01/23/1935 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    Text folder "Changes (sales & purchases) of investments since Sept. 1, 1934 with current cash balance of each fund."
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 12/04/1934 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Text on folder "re: New Science Building"
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 11/07/1934 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 05/09/1934 --06/08/1934 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    Text on folder "Sale of securities. Question of consolidated investments."
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 10/12/1933 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    Text on folder "Re: Securities"
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 03/25/1933 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    Text on folder "Re: Budget summary and increases. Reduction to balance budget. Investments."
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 02/01/1933 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    Text on folder "Re: Reinvestment of funds from: General Endowment, Scottish Rite, Pairo, Sale of Detroit Edisons & Commonwealth Edisons"
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 12/08/1932 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    Text on folder "Re: Inspection of Securities of Endowment Funds"
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 12/03/1931 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    Text on folder "Subject: Stocks & bonds of University"
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 11/14/1931 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    Text on folder "In re: 1) Clephane and Latimer bill 2) Summer Sessions budget 3) Repair budget 4) Repair budget 4) Pairo Estate"
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 03/26/1930 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    Text on folder "Re: Budget"
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 03/07/1930 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    Text on folder "Re: - 1) Refinancing University, Impaired Endowments, Other Obligations 2) Securities Purchases since last meeting - Dec. 3, 1929 3) School of Classical Studies at Athens"
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 12/03/1929 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    Text on folder "Re: Checking of Securities"
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 03/21/1929 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    Text on folder "Re: Fees - Medical, Law, Physical Education. Travel Allowance. Community Chest."
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 10/15/1928 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    Text on folder "Re: Investment of Funds. Administrative Reserve Funds. Examination of Securities. Appointment of Auditor. Changes in 1928-1929 Budget."
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 03/03/1928 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    Text on folder "Re: Investment of Funds."
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, 10/06/1927 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    Text on folder "Re: Accounting System. Reorganized Budget."
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, Correspondence, 1936 -1952 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, Correspondence and misc., 1921 -1935 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, Committee Materials, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Committee on Financial and Legal Affairs, Regulations of the Board of Trustees concerning Budget Appropriations, and Accounting for and Administration of Trust Funds, 05/31/1916 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence, 1942 -1950 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1951 -1960 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Lists of Recipients of Honorary Degrees, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Committee of Honors--correspondence and meeting minutes, 12/08/1960 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Text on folder "The Committee approved the conferring of the honorary degree of Doctor of Science on Acting President O.S. Colclough at the Winter Convocation on February 22, 1961. (no formal minutes taken at this meeting.)"
  - Committee of Honors--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/12/1960 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Text on folder "The Committee approved recommending the following honorary degrees be conferred at a Special Convocation on August 31, 1960: The right Hon. The Viscount Kilmuir LL.D., John Daniel Randall LL.D (no formal minutes taken at meeting)"
  - Committee of Honors--correspondence and meeting minutes, 03/09/1960 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Text on folder "(No minutes taken) It was agreed to recommend the following to receive degrees honoris causa to be conferred at the Commencement on June 1, 1960: James Plemon Coleman LL.D, Fred Korth LL.D, Jeremiah Milbank LL.D, Robert Smylie LL.D, Edward Teller Sc.D"
  - Committee of Honors--correspondence and meeting minutes, 12/10/1959 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Text on folder "It was agreed to recommend the following to receive honorary degrees at the Winter Convocation, February 22, 1960: David Edward Finley LL.D, Winfred Overholser LL.D (no formal minutes taken at meeting)"
  - Committee of Honors--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/14/1959 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Text on folder "The Committee approved recommending the following honorary degrees be conferred at Commencement on June 3, 1959: Harold Jefferson Coolidge Sc.D., Watson Davis Sc.D., Allen Welsh Dulles LL.D., James William Fulbright LL.D., Melville Bell Grosvenor LL.D. (Note: Mr. Coolidge was unable to be present at Commencement. His degree was awarded at Fall Convocation on October 17, 1959.) (no minutes taken at this meeting)"
  - Committee of Honors--correspondence and meeting minutes, 04/1958 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    Text on folder "The members of the Committee on Honors approved by correspondence the conferring of the following honorary degrees at the Commencement on June 4, 1958: Allen Varley Astin Sc.D., Walter Maximillian Bastian LL.D., Daniel LeRay Borden Sc.D., Wilber Marion Brucker LL.D., Robert Daniel Murphy LL.D., Charles Sylvanus Rhyne D.C.L. The degree Litt.D. is to be conferred on Benjamin Mosby McKelway at the Fall Convocation on October 18, 1958."
  - Committee of Honors--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/22/1958 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    Text on folder "Preceding the Convocation on February 22, 1958, the Committee on Honors authorized the conferring of the following degrees: Margaret Chase Smith, Doctor of Laws, Louis Booker Wright, Doctor of Laws (No minutes were taken at this meeting)"
  - Committee of Honors--correspondence and meeting minutes, 11/22/1957 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Text on folder "The Committee approved the conferring of the honorary degree of Doctor of Laws on the King of Morocco on Wednesday, November 27, 1957."
  - Committee of Honors--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/21/1957 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    Text on folder "Recommendation that the following persons receive degrees honoris causa: On Feb. 22, 1957: Robert Whitney Bolwell Doctor of Letters Litt.D. On June 5, 1957: Newell Windom Ellison Doctor of Laws LL.D., Philbrick McCoy Doctor of Laws LL.D., Robert Clement Watson Doctor of Laws LL.D."
  - Committee of Honors--correspondence and meeting minutes, 11/22/1955 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    Text on folder "Honorary degree recommendations for Drs. Dryden and Astin referred to Trustee Brigs and President Marvin for study and recommendation; consideration to be given to dedicating a convocation to honoring four or five scientists. Honorary degrees approved for: Luis Battle Berres - Dec. 7, 1955, Bumpei Kure - in absentia, Clarence Aiken Aspinwall - Feb. 22, '56, Ulysses S. Grant, III - Feb. 22, 1956, Alfred Henry Lawson, - Feb. 22, 1956, Leon Carmichael - Feb. 22, 1956"
  - Committee of Honors--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/29/1942 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    Text on folder "Report of the Chairman to the Board: Edwin Martin Watson, Doctor of Laws, Ross T. McIntire, Doctor of Science"
  - Committee of Honors--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/25/1939 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Committee of Honors--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/20/1937 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    Text on folder "re: Commencement (honorary degrees) June 9, 1937"
  - Committee of Honors--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/20/1936 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Committee of Honors--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/13/1935 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    Text on folder "Honorary degrees - Feb. 22, 1935 - Convocation"
  - Committee of Honors--correspondence and meeting minutes, 04/18/1934 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    Text on folder "Cordell Hull, John L. Newcomb, Arthur Cutts Willard - others considered"
  - Committee of Honors--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/1932 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    Text on folder "Medical Convocation - Honorary degrees to Chesney, Robinson, Gay"
  - Committee of Honors--Re: Buckner Magill Randolph made Emeritus Professor of Clinical Medicine, 03/25/1930 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    Text on folder "Re: Buckner Magill Randolph made Emeritus Professor of Clinical Medicine"
  - Committee of Honors--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/18/1930 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    Text on folder "Re: - Names considered: Harry C. Evans, Thorwald Solberg, Walter McFarland, Rev. Bernard Braskamp, Louis D. Bliss, Harrison Howall Dodge, Lotus Delta Coffman"
  - Committee of Honors--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/28/1929 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    Text on folder "Papers considered: Grace W. Brosseau, Edgar Cordell Powers, Wendell P. Stafford, President Y.C. Yang, Professor E. Allison Peers, Professor M.A. DeVitis"
  - Committee of Honors--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/15/1928 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    Text on folder "Papers considered: J.W. Crabtree, Harrison Dodge, Arthur Stanley Riggs, Sterling Ruffin, Thorwald Solberg, Paul Wilstach. Degrees approved: David Allan Robertson, William Fletcher Russell, Harlan Fiske Stone"
  - Committee on University Hospital--Correspondence, undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Report of the Committee on the Univ. Hospital to the Board of Trustees, undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Committee on University Hospital--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/02/1960 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    Text on folder "The Committee voted to recommend approval by the Board of Trustees of the Report of the Hospital Committee to the Board of Trustees concerning the Medical Center Development Program,"
  - Committee on University Hospital--correspondence and meeting minutes, 03/04/1960 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    Text on folder "Discussion of the ten-year expansion plan of the Hospital, including plans for a new wing in the near future."
  - Committee on University Hospital--correspondence and meeting minutes, 04/27/1959 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    Text on folder "Discussion of the rest of the proposed revisions of the By-Laws, Rules, and Regulations Governing the Medical Staff of the University Hospital. The Committee voted to recommend the adoption of the By-Laws... as revised to the Board of Trustees. The Committee adjourned."
  - Committee on Public Relations--meeting minutes, 01/27/1955 (Box 6, Folder 1)